<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-01T05:58:43+00:00</updated><id>https://insilijo.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Anti-Governance, Original Sin, and Conway’s Law</title><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/divergence-and-failure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anti-Governance, Original Sin, and Conway’s Law"/><published>2026-01-27T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-27T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/divergence-and-failure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/divergence-and-failure/"><![CDATA[<p>Loss through human divergence is a recurring motif across mythologies and modern narratives. Whether it’s the Tower of Babel, <em>Anna Karenina</em>, or Apple TV’s <em>Pluribus</em>, coherence is portrayed as fragile: something briefly held within a community before fragmenting under competing perspectives, incentives, or truths.</p> <p>Organizations face the same problem. We are increasingly aware of our fractured knowledge (<a href="/blog/2026/scientific-babylon/">as explored here</a>) and we even possess idealized models for addressing it (<a href="/blog/2026/catalog-of-catalogs/">outlined here</a>). And yet, more often than not, we find ourselves in a disequilibrium between data in and meaning out.</p> <p>Functional organizations are alike: clear ownership, shared purpose, and mechanisms for resolving conflicts or operational differences as they evolve. Dysfunctional organizations, by contrast, fail in many different ways. Those failures are not random. They tend to fracture along the same structural seams, where decisions were deferred, authority was ambiguous, or tradeoffs were never made explicit.</p> <p>In scientific organizations, these fractures are especially visible because messy, expensive, large, complex, and regulated data magnifies them. When coherence breaks down, it does so predictably by eroding structure, dissolving focus, or overwhelming orchestration. What follows are not edge cases or cultural quirks, but recurring governance failures that turn abundance into noise.</p> <p>In the context of scientific data systems, I’ll outline five such failure modes.</p> <h2 id="original-sin">Original Sin</h2> <p>Every data system inherits its earliest assumptions. Those assumptions are almost never wrong, but they are always incomplete.</p> <p>Early success hardens into structure before its implications are understood or felt. In scientific organizations, this usually happens at moments of genuine discovery that translates to early commercial success or funding. A postdoc identifies a compound with higher efficacy and lower toxicity. A mid-career scientist devises a scalable manufacturing process for a difficult protein. The work is real, urgent, and valuable.</p> <p>At that moment, no one asks how these results should be schematized, governed, or made durable. They shouldn’t. The goal is progress, not architecture.</p> <p>But early decisions – from file formats, to identifiers, naming conventions, database structures, knowledge limits, ownership boundaries – quietly fix the future shape of the system. What begins as a pragmatic shortcut becomes a moral commitment. Downstream teams inherit constraints they did not choose, and over time those constraints, now inscrutable, are mistaken for deified intent.</p> <p>Original Sin is not bad design. It is unexamined design, preserved long past the conditions that justified it.</p> <h2 id="underinvestment-in-stewardship">Underinvestment in Stewardship</h2> <p>As organizations evolve, they must become increasingly selective with resources. Early success often encourages investment in technology: more scientists, more direct support, more output. During periods of strategic repositioning, those same organizations may assume that existing systems are robust enough to persist with less attention. Even in uneventful drift, as stewards move on to new roles or opportunities, institutional protections quietly decay.</p> <p>The underlying assumption is that something built correctly (or even fit for purpose) will last indefinitely. It won’t.</p> <p>Stewardship is an unassuming function. Its greatest yields are negative space: fewer disruptions, smoother access, less friction. These outcomes rarely excite investors or justify headcount. Failure is also slow. Platforms corrode gradually; they almost never collapse outright.</p> <p>Stewardship is not a technical role. It is an organizational function and an institutional posture. When it is underinvested, the closest contributors to the pain points often compensate through yeomanlike labor, building informal workarounds or cottage industries of reconciliation. To leadership, this can appear efficient. In reality, it externalizes cost.</p> <p>The burden of maintaining coherence shifts downstream. New hires have to play games of telephone and archaeology, adjacent teams must support domain knowledge they don’t have, and end users who must reconstruct context that was never preserved. Over time, the organization becomes dependent on memory rather than structure.</p> <p>Stewardship is the work of maintaining meaning across time. When it is absent, systems do not fail loudly; they rot quietly.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-27/garfield-existentialism.avif" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-27/garfield-existentialism.avif" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">Garfield Minus Garfield: Existentialism. Jim Davis and Dan Walsh</figcaption> </figure> <h2 id="organic-growth">Organic Growth</h2> <p>Organizations are never born just once. They pass through a series of transitions: promising platforms give way to new candidates, technologies are adopted, programs are cut, teams re-form, and key personnel move on. Throughout these changes, data continues to accumulate. What changes is not volume, but direction.</p> <p>It is natural to assume that methods which worked previously will continue to work. During transitions, however, pressure mounts. Deadlines tighten, scope shifts, and small deviations become necessary. A workaround is introduced to accommodate an edge case or unblock progress. The change functions, delivers value, and – crucially – appears harmless.</p> <p>At this point, a choice exists: reconcile the exception back into the system by extending the schema, revising constraints, or explicitly redefining scope. Or leave it alone.</p> <p>Organic overgrowth occurs when reconciliation is deferred. The workaround takes root outside the original structure, not as an intentional fork, but as a practical accommodation. Over time, these local optimizations proliferate. They remain functional, even useful, but increasingly distinct. What began as a single exception becomes a parallel record of truth.</p> <p>This is how competing ontologies emerge in good faith. A table is created without key relationships. Clinical trial metadata lives in a PowerPoint because it is visible and fast. A secondary identifier system is introduced to satisfy an urgent need. Each choice is rational in isolation. Collectively, they fracture coherence.</p> <p>The danger is not that these systems fail. It is that they succeed. Parallel frameworks demand duplicate effort, require constant translation, and resist consolidation because they are already embedded in workflows. Overgrowth is difficult to reverse precisely because nothing is broken.</p> <p>Organic overgrowth is entropy mistaken for flexibility. Without deliberate reconciliation, systems expand outward instead of upward, accumulating exceptions until the cost of unification outweighs the will to attempt it.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-27/myst-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-27/myst-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-27/myst-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-27/myst.jpg" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">Myst library from https://www.trueachievements.com/game/Myst/walkthrough/3. Rand and Robyn Miller, Cyan, 1993. I will not be taking further questions.</figcaption> </figure> <h2 id="conways-law">Conway’s Law</h2> <p>“Any organization that designs a system (defined broadly) will produce a design whose structure is a copy of the organization’s communication structure.” — Melvin Conway, 1968</p> <p>Melvin Conway’s observation is often treated as a technical curiosity: a two-person team builds a two-pass compiler, a four-person team builds a four-pass one. In practice, it describes far more than software architecture. It applies equally to organizations, data systems, and the knowledge structures that emerge from them.</p> <p>At its core, Conway’s Law is neutral. Structure follows communication. Decisions follow authority. Boundaries propagate. X begets Y.</p> <p>It becomes a failure mode when X is already compromised.</p> <p>Knowledge systems are not abstract representations of truth; they are accumulations of decisions, incentives, and justifications made by an organization at a specific moment in time. They encode not only what is known, but who was allowed to decide, who needed to be consulted, and which tradeoffs were acceptable. When communication paths fragment, so does meaning.</p> <p>Because decisions are cumulative, small disruptions matter. A temporary reporting line becomes permanent. A workaround becomes precedent. A silenced stakeholder becomes an absent domain. Over time, the structure of the organization becomes its intent, and that intent determines the structure of the system.</p> <p>This is why Conway’s Law is not merely descriptive but predictive. Systems do not fail because they are poorly designed. They fail because they faithfully mirror organizations that are themselves in flux, misaligned, or fragmented.</p> <p>Conway’s Law explains why coherence cannot be fixed downstream. When communication breaks, architecture follows. When authority diffuses, meaning fractures. The system does not resist this outcome: it records it.</p> <h2 id="unwillingness-to-revise">Unwillingness to Revise</h2> <p>All of these failure modes carry an element of inevitability. The future cannot be predicted, so the present cannot be perfectly constructed around it. Our flexibility can be a strength but can limit focus and our best attempts at orchestration can become outdated or misdirected.</p> <p>Left unmitigated, these dynamics can degrade systems. But none of them represent terminal failure. What <strong>is</strong> terminal is the unwillingness to confront them.</p> <p>Revision is a fact of scientific life. Until 1944, proteins were thought to carry genetic information. Until the late nineteenth century, disease was attributed to miasma rather than microbes. Science isn’t conducted by predicting, preserving, or even finding correct answers, but by revising frameworks when evidence demands it.</p> <p>As scientists, we accept that hypotheses must change. The same principle must apply to how we record, structure, and govern our knowledge. When existing systems obstruct interpretation or decision-making, they must be revised, regardless of how successful or familiar they once were.</p> <p>This is rarely easy. Revision is both technical and political. It requires deep institutional understanding and legitimate authority, a combination that is seldom concentrated in a single role. As a result, revision often occurs only when failure becomes visible enough to bridge the gap between technical insight and executive action. That can be too late in a competitive landscape.</p> <p>But without revision, failure modes compound. Original assumptions harden. Stewardship erodes. Exceptions proliferate. Organizational fractures imprint themselves onto systems. What begins as manageable drift becomes structural decay.</p> <p>Revision is the only counterforce. It must be deliberate, authorized, and decisive. Without it, systems do not merely age; they accumulate incoherence and fracture into individual, incompatible truths.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="software"/><category term="science"/><category term="ontologies"/><category term="standards"/><category term="omics"/><category term="multiomics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA["All happy families are alike; each unhappy family is unhappy in its own way." - Leo Tolstoy]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why it’s so hard to feed people</title><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/why-its-hard-to-feed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why it’s so hard to feed people"/><published>2026-01-27T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-27T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/why-its-hard-to-feed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/why-its-hard-to-feed/"><![CDATA[<p>In 1939, John Steinbeck wrote a haunting passage about the real source of hunger in the Dust Bowl and Great Depression:</p> <blockquote> <p>The works of the roots of the vines, of the trees, must be destroyed to keep up the price, and this is the saddest, bitterest thing of all. Carloads of oranges dumped on the ground. The people came for miles to take the fruit, but this could not be. How would they buy oranges at twenty cents a dozen if they could drive out and pick them up? And men with hoses squirt kerosene on the oranges, and they are angry at the crime, angry at the people who have come to take the fruit. A million people hungry, needing the fruit - and kerosene sprayed over the golden mountains. And the smell of rot fills the country. Burn coffee for fuel in the ships. Burn corn to keep warm, it makes a hot fire. Dump potatoes in the rivers and place guards along the banks to keep the hungry people from fishing them out. Slaughter the pigs and bury them, and let the putrescence drip down into the earth. <br/> <br/> There is a crime here that goes beyond denunciation. <br/> <br/> There is a sorrow here that weeping cannot symbolize. <br/> <br/> There is a failure here that topples all our success. <br/> <br/> The fertile earth, the straight tree rows, the sturdy trunks, and the ripe fruit. And children dying of pellagra must die because a profit cannot be taken from an orange. And coroners must fill in the certificate - died of malnutrition - because the food must rot, must be forced to rot. The people come with nets to fish for potatoes in the river, and the guards hold them back; they come in rattling cars to get the dumped oranges, but the kerosene is sprayed. And they stand still and watch the potatoes float by, listen to the screaming pigs being killed in a ditch and covered with quick-lime, watch the mountains of oranges slop down to a putrefying ooze; and in the eyes of the people there is the failure; and in the eyes of the hungry there is a growing wrath. In the souls of the people the grapes of wrath are filling and growing heavy, growing heavy for the vintage.</p> </blockquote> <ul> <li>John Steinbeck, <em>The Grapes of Wrath</em></li> </ul> <p>What Steinbeck identifies as most disturbing is not the hunger itself or even the diagnosis of a clear villain that leads to it. There is no cartoonish president directly promoting genocide, no subversive group of wealthy individuals advocating for hunger, not even a <em>Phytophthora infestans</em> blighting the crops as it did during the Irish Potato Famine. Instead, there’s the quiet and bleak assumption that – sometimes – many have to be sacrificed to keep the machine of industry running, even if it results in obvious inefficiency.</p> <p>Even in Boston — a city with high transit access, strong social programs, and deep institutional wealth — food insecurity remains widespread. 37% of Massachusetts families report facing food insecurity and nearly <a href="https://www.boston.gov/news/mayor-wu-boston-officials-share-local-response-looming-lapse-snap-benefits">20% rely</a> directly on SNAP assistance to make ends meet (<a href="https://www.gbfb.org/news/press-releases/2025-annual-statewide-food-access-report/">see the report</a>).</p> <p>So how can we be so wealthy and so poor at the same time?</p> <h2 id="what-do-we-know">What Do We Know?</h2> <p>General statistics tell a big part of the story. Boston has a rich history, and unfortunately a segregated history. Research suggests that demographics are the biggest predictor with 62% of Hispanic households, 46% of Black households, and 56% of LGBTQIA+ households facing insecurity from the same report as above.</p> <p>Indeed, neighborhood-level maps support this theory, with communities of color like Roxbury, Dorchester, and Mattapan disproportionately affected.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-left"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/food-insecurity-neighborhood-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/food-insecurity-neighborhood-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/food-insecurity-neighborhood-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/food-insecurity-neighborhood.png" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">SNAP Access by Neighborhood. City of Boston Food Access: Food Access and Insecurity.</figcaption> </figure> <p>While the city of Boston, predominantly through the Greater Boston Food Bank, distributes nearly 90 million healthy meals to 190 cities and towns in Eastern Massachusetts while operating over 600 community-based pantries. Massachusetts, as a whole, distributes over <a href="https://www.cbpp.org/research/food-assistance/snap-state-by-state-data-fact-sheets-and-resources">$2.6 billion</a> dollars to food assistance in the state.</p> <p>Despite this, <a href="https://www.boston.gov/news/mayor-wu-mass-general-brigham-and-ymca-greater-boston-announce-new-cold-storage-infrastructure">Boston’s Office of Food Justice (OFJ) along with the National Resources Development Council (NRDC)</a> estimates that 21% of all of Boston’s waste – 130,000 tons – is food, with an additional 1,100 that could be recovered through further interventions.</p> <p>The demand is there, and the supply is there. If markets alone solved coordination problems, hunger would already be rare.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/water_delivery_2x-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/water_delivery_2x-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/water_delivery_2x-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/water_delivery_2x.png" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">Randall Munroe. https://xkcd.com/1599/. When I was a kid, I asked my parents why our houses didn't have toothpaste pipes in addition to water ones. I'm strangely pleased to see Amazon thinking the same way.</figcaption> </figure> <p>The problem isn’t quantity, it’s logistics. Our typical response to hunger isn’t to meet it where it is, it’s to meet it where it <em>visibly</em> is. Boston homelessness is at 2.4% and mostly concentrated in a multi-block radius around a few sites downtown near MGH at “Mass and Cass” or “Methadone Mile”, North Roxbury/the South End, and in Jamaica Plain near Southeast Franklin Park at the Shattuck Shelter Pine Street Inn.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-left"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/food-pantries-neighborhood-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/food-pantries-neighborhood-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/food-pantries-neighborhood-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/food-pantries-neighborhood.png" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">Food Pantries by Neighborhood. City of Boston Food Access: Food Access and Insecurity.</figcaption> </figure> <p>With the exception of Jamaica Plain, there is significant concentration of service for food pantries in the denser, visibly homeless areas. This is great; these people need food – especially fresh food – and direct access.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-left"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/boston-cost-per-room-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/boston-cost-per-room-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/boston-cost-per-room-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-02-02/boston-cost-per-room.png" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">Food Pantries by Neighborhood. City of Boston Food Access: Food Access and Insecurity.</figcaption> </figure> <p>However, we’re seeing a negligence of a vast amount of people who would meet that “food insecure” label and claim SNAP. Indeed, the locations with the <em>highest median cost per room</em> are very near the locations of food pantries in the downtown, Back Bay, Fenway, South End, and South Boston regions, right where the food pantries are.</p> <h2 id="what-exactly-are-we-doing-here">What Exactly Are We Doing Here?</h2> <p>We have a functional food delivery apparatus, a lot of food, and a lot of people willing to resolve hunger. But there remains a lot of hunger. We’re still in Steinbeck’s America.</p> <p>The people most consistently missed by the emergency food system are not the unhoused, but the “working poor”. These people – parents, blue-collar workers, and students – are too far from food pantries and too busy to get there. They’re stuck in a twilight zone of doing everything right but losing access as a result.</p> <p>The data we have aren’t sufficient. We fall prey to the same modes of decision-making that I’ve discussed before: <a href="/blog/2026/scientific-babylon/">many people who need to work together</a>, <a href="/blog/2026/catalog-of-catalogs/">speak different professional languages</a>, and <a href="/blog/2026/divergence-and-failure/">repeatedly fail to translate between them</a>.</p> <p>In this case, we have people with money trying to find the right way to leverage it by buying food and labor from the people who have it so they can give it to the communities with the greatest impact. But if you ask a politician, they’re looking at the figures above or listening to disgruntled community members driving by Mass and Cass. If you’re the Greater Boston Food Bank or the YMCA or one of the many other wonderful organizations, you’re trying to balance volunteering, minimal monetary resources, and centralized logistics to maximize output. If you’re a grocery store, farmers’ market, or food importer, you’re trying to maximize revenue but also minimize waste. And if you’re a community advocate, you see your neighbors and can say – directly – to whom the food should go.</p> <p>There are a lot of experts we need to integrate with different ontologies but one goal.</p> <p>People are forgotten because we’ve lost revision, the ability to update systems when reality shifts. We collect data, but acting on it is either decentralized or divorced from local needs. Local groups do really good work and cities are actively pursuing zero waste and food distribution initiatives. But the connective tissue – acting concurrently at a county and neighborhood level – means that the working poor are forgotten. Hunger persists not because food is scarce, but because distribution requires local context that centralized systems are structurally bad at representing.</p> <p>(I look forward to discussing solutions in future posts.)</p> <p>Maps taken from https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/956debdf80c0492bbceeedff9f6a4bac”.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="charity"/><category term="giving"/><category term="nonprofits"/><category term="context"/><category term="data"/><category term="ontologies"/><category term="food-justice"/><category term="food-waste"/><category term="logistics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The logistical and contextual challenge of reducing food waste and giving it to our neediest]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Catalog of Catalogs</title><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/catalog-of-catalogs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Catalog of Catalogs"/><published>2026-01-20T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-20T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/catalog-of-catalogs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/catalog-of-catalogs/"><![CDATA[<p>“This much is known: for every rational line or forthright statement there are leagues of senseless cacophony, verbal nonsense, and incoherency.” — Jorge Luis Borges, The Library of Babel</p> <p>In 1941, Borges imagined a universe in which the limitation of knowledge was not scarcity but excess. Every possible book existed, yet nothing was meaningfully accessible. In this world, the librarian’s hope rests on a mythical object: a <em>Catalog of Catalogs</em>, a structure that might impose order on overwhelming noise, and the Book-Man, who has studied it.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-right"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/Desmazieres-biblio-alphabet1-sm.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/Desmazieres-biblio-alphabet1-sm.webp" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">Erik Desmazieres, 1997, <i>La Bibliothèque de Babel</i> (above and thumbnail) for Le Livre Contermporain and Les Bibliophiles Franco-Suisses.</figcaption> </figure> <p>In 2026, modern scientific organizations increasingly resemble Borges’ library. Data accumulates faster than meaning can be maintained, and organization becomes the difference between insight and noise. We’re not faced with a lack of quantitative or qualitative metrics, we’re faced with a lack of coherence.</p> <p><a href="/blog/2026/scientific-babylon/">Last week, I wrote about how the crucial endeavor in science is getting people with fundamentally different expertises to talk to each other</a>. I focused a lot on ontologies as a mechanism of that record, and how both subject matter and translational governance are underestimated infrastructure. Borges’ allegory of the <em>Catalog of Catalogs</em> and the Book-Man are particularly prescient here; it’s not knowledge being sought but the demand for structured knowledge. We’re all looking for a template by which to organize the data and someone who can make sense of it and therefore lead us into a kind of distillation where the infinite becomes comprehensible to the finite.</p> <p>This structured knowledge doesn’t exist by accident. Instead, it’s a very active process of structure, focus, and then orchestration: a “what”, a “why”, and a “how”.</p> <h3 id="structure">Structure</h3> <p>The first concern is that data be reasonably segmented and relational. From a practical standpoint, data must be Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable (FAIR). If not, data tend to be labyrinthine, bottlenecked, or plainly incoherent.</p> <p>We’ve all lived in organizations where we’ve had to wade through years of previous colleagues’ Excel files, sandbox analyses, hopes, and dreams. Correctly structured data maintain relevance and a paper trail for a broad swath of the organization without unnecessary bureaucracy.</p> <p>A lot of focus is put on the first two elements (findable and accessible), but interoperable and reusable data are equally important. It’s crucial that data maintain relation to other data while functioning broadly across contexts. Structure presents the “where” and the “how” of coherence.</p> <h3 id="focus">Focus</h3> <p>Structure frames and orients knowledge, but it does not direct it. Most organizations do not lack data; they lack agreement about which questions matter. Focus provides the bridge between what is technically possible and what is operationally relevant.</p> <p>In the absence of focus, data systems become encyclopedic rather than instrumental: impressive in scope, but disconnected from decision-making. Everything is recorded, nothing is prioritized, and insight is deferred indefinitely.</p> <p>Focus requires constraint. It means explicitly defining:</p> <ul> <li>which problems are in scope,</li> <li>which audiences the data serve,</li> <li>and which uses are not supported.</li> </ul> <p>Focus is an acknowledgment that not all pursuits are equally valuable and that excluding irrelevance is a prerequisite for action. Focus is where knowledge ceases being merely reflective and starts becoming useful.</p> <h3 id="orchestration">Orchestration</h3> <p>Where structured, focused data enable valuable prototypes, orchestration is what allows those systems to scale. It is no accident that modern computational frameworks (whether data architecture, DevOps, or agentic systems) borrow musical terminology: orchestration is the work of getting multiple competent functions to operate coherently through change. The way we use our data must mirror what we expect from it.</p> <p>Orchestration requires stewardship and governance. It is the ongoing maintenance of alignment between structure, focus, and reality as systems grow. Initial models of data flow are necessary, but insufficient; organizations must adapt as methods change, incentives shift, and markets evolve. That adaptability does not emerge spontaneously. It requires deliberate ownership, revision authority, and sustained care.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/man_of_action-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/man_of_action-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/man_of_action-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/man_of_action.gif" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small"><i>Calvin and Hobbes: Man of Action</i> by Bill Watterson. September 21, 1993</figcaption> </figure> <p>When Borges wrote about his library, he did so appealing to the philosophical arrangement of knowledge and how we make sense of the world. In this perfect and infinite arrangement of all possible things that could be described, his best case still was seeking a digested, comprehensible version of it.</p> <p>In scientific systems, it’s our reality to take pragmatic approaches to our expanding means of measuring and describing the world. Whether we’re collecting and making decisions in the current AI revolution, the “Big Data” boom of the last decade, or Borges’ 1941, we’re still restricted by the same conditions.</p> <p>No amount of technological advancement can replace our core need for coherence, not completeness, in data. The limiting factor has never been measurement, storage, or computation. It has always been our willingness to decide what matters, who decides it, and who is accountable when meaning breaks.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="software"/><category term="science"/><category term="data"/><category term="ontologies"/><category term="standards"/><category term="omics"/><category term="multiomics"/><category term="coherence"/><category term="strategy"/><category term="governance"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Coherence, not completeness, is the limiting factor of data in modern scientific organizations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific Babylon</title><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/scientific-babylon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific Babylon"/><published>2026-01-10T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-10T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/scientific-babylon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/scientific-babylon/"><![CDATA[<p>In accounts from The Bible and The Torah, the Tower of Babel is built to prevent a second flood, only to result in the fragmentation of human language. Variations on the same theme appear across Greek, Estonian, Sumerian, and Aztec traditions: a once-unified humanity loses a shared understanding of the world through linguistic division. In these stories, collective power gives way to confusion: not through catastrophe, but through meaning itself.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-right"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/tower_of_babylon-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/tower_of_babylon-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/tower_of_babylon-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/tower_of_babylon.jpg" width="100%" height="auto" alt="The Tower of Babel By Pieter Brueghel the Elder - Levels adjusted from File:Pieter_Bruegel_the_Elder_-_The_Tower_of_Babel_(Vienna)_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg, originally from Google Art Project., Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=22179117" title="The Tower of Babel By Pieter Brueghel the Elder - Levels adjusted from File:Pieter_Bruegel_the_Elder_-_The_Tower_of_Babel_(Vienna)_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg, originally from Google Art Project., Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=22179117" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">The Tower of Babel By Pieter Brueghel the Elder - Levels adjusted from File:Pieter_Bruegel_the_Elder_-_The_Tower_of_Babel_(Vienna)_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg, originally from Google Art Project., Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=22179117</figcaption> </figure> <p>Modern linguistics offers a less mythic explanation. Languages diverge naturally, shaped by ecology, geography, isolation, and social structure. Language is not merely a labeling system; it is a lens for interpreting a complex world. As perspectives diverge, so too must the structures used to describe them.</p> <p>Science faces a related, but sharper, problem. We attempt to describe systems that are not only complex, but mostly unobservable, probabilistic, and dynamic. The challenge extends past measurement and into representation: data are meaningless without a structured, shared, and preserved system. That system has to subscribe to the same orders as all data: Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reproducible (FAIR) because its value lies in how it interfaces with colleagues and other data.</p> <p>Ontologies attempt to resolve this fragmentation by enforcing shared meaning. Here, ontology is used in its applied sense: not as a claim about what exists, but as a practical expression of how knowledge is organized and exchanged. In practice, they often expose the cost of assuming meaning can be fixed at all. Applying an alternative standard to these processes – instead of resulting in meaning – adds another standard on top of the dozens already there. We confront our own Tower of Babel, then: we find ourselves playing a massive, expensive game of telephone where meaning is exchanged, lost, and mutated between experts.</p> <p>In metabolomics alone, biological, chemical, and analytical vocabularies coexist; each developed in different ecologies, each optimized for a different audience, and each only partially compatible with the others.</p> <p>These ontologies operate <strong>long before</strong> interpretation is even possible. Moreover, each individual discipline involved is nuanced, requiring years of experience or education to get to foundational understanding. These ontologies are the connective tissue that flattens these disciplinary nuances. For example, metabolomics data flows from Liquid Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (LC/MS) through reference spectra (ideally developed on the same machine and method) and finally to a format that’s accessible to a biochemist (typically a table). Even in this simplified process, it’s clear that there’s a substantial amount of effort involved in developing the method, creating the infrastructure around managing/storing the data, selecting/synthesizing reference compounds, analyzing data, and engineering it for interpretation.</p> <p>Even getting to the point where we’re comfortable analyzing the data requires a tremendous amount of effort and coordination. Moreover, no scientist has the capacity or time to ensure quality of the product, and relies on the data originator to deliver precise, accurate, and relevant results. It’s crucial, for both internal and external purposes, to maintain a paper trail that makes it clear how each step integrates into the useful data. Otherwise, we’re left with a mess of isolated numbers.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-left"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/xkcd_927_standards-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/xkcd_927_standards-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/xkcd_927_standards-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/xkcd_927_standards.png" width="360" height="auto" alt="xkcd 927 Standards comic" title="xkcd 927 Standards comic" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">xkcd 927 &quot;Standards&quot; by Randall Munroe, CC BY-NC 2.5, https://xkcd.com/927/</figcaption> </figure> <p>This isn’t just a factor in metabolomics. In fact, this specific analytical example can be applied directly to proteomics with a few small tweaks. Genomics, too, can claim to have done an excellent job of exploiting integrated analytics and ontologies to create reliable, consistent pipelines that are broadly interpretable and trustworthy. What we’re trying to do here – use extremely expensive, sensitive instruments on extremely expensive, sensitive biological samples – is difficult and important. The first step is being able to adequately describe what’s going on to other people.</p> <p>Ontologies are, at their most useful, a representation of shared purpose among diverse methods, all integrating into a cohesive representation of an intractable phenomenon. To get to that point, it requires often silent, detailed labor from a large group of people to map out and maintain a reliable pipeline. However, they can often fall prone to overly-calcified standards, resulting in a labyrinthine branched set of systems. These processes must reflect their application while remaining integrated with their partners. To do this, ontologies are most effective when they constrain interpretation without attempting to freeze meaning. In domains that evolve as quickly as medicine, chemistry, tech, and biology, representation must remain thoughtfully provisional without becoming unstable.</p> <p>What looks like a problem of standards is often a problem of governance. The failure mode here is rarely technical. It is organizational. Different groups optimize for different incentives, audiences, or realities – speed, precision, publication, novelty, regulatory defensibility, commercial relevance – and ontologies become the battleground where those incentives collide. Standardization does not remove ambiguity; it decides who bears the cost of resolving it.</p> <p>In practice, governance does not mean tighter standards or different hiring practices. It means deciding who can revise definitions, how translation is handled, and where ambiguity is tolerated. Meaning will change regardless; the real question is who is accountable for managing that change over time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="software"/><category term="science"/><category term="ontologies"/><category term="standards"/><category term="omics"/><category term="multiomics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An essay on how meaning, incentives, and governance shape scientific systems across teams and institutions.]]></summary></entry></feed>