<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-21T01:33:59+00:00</updated><id>https://insilijo.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Catalog of Catalogs</title><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/catalog-of-catalogs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Catalog of Catalogs"/><published>2026-01-20T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-20T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/catalog-of-catalogs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/catalog-of-catalogs/"><![CDATA[<p>“This much is known: for every rational line or forthright statement there are leagues of senseless cacophony, verbal nonsense, and incoherency.” — Jorge Luis Borges, The Library of Babel</p> <p>In 1941, Borges imagined a universe in which the limitation of knowledge was not scarcity but excess. Every possible book existed, yet nothing was meaningfully accessible. In this world, the librarian’s hope rests on a mythical object: a <em>Catalog of Catalogs</em>, a structure that might impose order on overwhelming noise, and the Book-Man, who has studied it.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-right"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/Desmazieres-biblio-alphabet1-sm.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/Desmazieres-biblio-alphabet1-sm.webp" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">Erik Desmazieres, 1997, __La Bibliothèque de Babel__ (above and thumbnail) for Le Livre Contermporain and Les Bibliophiles Franco-Suisses.</figcaption> </figure> <p>In 2026, modern scientific organizations increasingly resemble Borges’ library. Data accumulates faster than meaning can be maintained, and organization becomes the difference between insight and noise. We’re not faced with a lack of quantitative or qualitative metrics, we’re faced with a lack of coherence.</p> <p><a href="/blog/2026/scientific-babylon/">Last week, I wrote about how the crucial endeavor in science is getting people with fundamentally different expertises to talk to each other</a>. I focused a lot on ontologies as a mechanism of that record, and how both subject matter and translational governance are underestimated infrastructure. Borges’ allegory of the <em>Catalog of Catalogs</em> and the Book-Man are particularly prescient here; it’s not knowledge being sought but the demand for structured knowledge. We’re all looking for a template by which to organize the data and someone who can make sense of it and therefore lead us into a kind of distillation where the infinite becomes comprehensible to the finite.</p> <p>This structured knowledge doesn’t exist by accident. Instead, it’s a very active process of structure, focus, and then orchestration: a “what”, a “why”, and a “how”.</p> <h3 id="structure">Structure</h3> <p>The first concern is that data be reasonably segmented and relational. From a practical standpoint, data must be Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable (FAIR). If not, data tend to be labyrinthine, bottlenecked, or plainly incoherent.</p> <p>We’ve all lived in organizations where we’ve had to wade through years of previous colleagues’ Excel files, sandbox analyses, hopes, and dreams. Correctly structured data maintain relevance and a paper trail for a broad swath of the organization without unnecessary bureaucracy.</p> <p>A lot of focus is put on the first two elements (findable and accessible), but interoperable and reusable data are equally important. It’s crucial that data maintain relation to other data while functioning broadly across contexts. Structure presents the “where” and the “how” of coherence.</p> <h3 id="focus">Focus</h3> <p>Structure frames and orients knowledge, but it does not direct it. Most organizations do not lack data; they lack agreement about which questions matter. Focus provides the bridge between what is technically possible and what is operationally relevant.</p> <p>In the absence of focus, data systems become encyclopedic rather than instrumental: impressive in scope, but disconnected from decision-making. Everything is recorded, nothing is prioritized, and insight is deferred indefinitely.</p> <p>Focus requires constraint. It means explicitly defining:</p> <ul> <li>which problems are in scope,</li> <li>which audiences the data serve,</li> <li>and which uses are not supported.</li> </ul> <p>Focus is an acknowledgment that not all pursuits are equally valuable and that excluding irrelevance is a prerequisite for action. Focus is where knowledge ceases being merely reflective and starts becoming useful.</p> <h3 id="orchestration">Orchestration</h3> <p>Where structured, focused data enable valuable prototypes, orchestration is what allows those systems to scale. It is no accident that modern computational frameworks (whether data architecture, DevOps, or agentic systems) borrow musical terminology: orchestration is the work of getting multiple competent functions to operate coherently through change. The way we use our data must mirror what we expect from it.</p> <p>Orchestration requires stewardship and governance. It is the ongoing maintenance of alignment between structure, focus, and reality as systems grow. Initial models of data flow are necessary, but insufficient; organizations must adapt as methods change, incentives shift, and markets evolve. That adaptability does not emerge spontaneously. It requires deliberate ownership, revision authority, and sustained care.</p> <figure class="inline-figure"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/man_of_action-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/man_of_action-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/man_of_action-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-20/man_of_action.gif" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">Calvin and Hobbes: Man of Action by Bill Watterson. September 21, 1993</figcaption> </figure> <p>When Borges wrote about his library, he did so appealing to the philosophical arrangement of knowledge and how we make sense of the world. In this perfect and infinite arrangement of all possible things that could be described, his best case still was seeking a digested, comprehensible version of it.</p> <p>In scientific systems, it’s our reality to take pragmatic approaches to our expanding means of measuring and describing the world. Whether we’re collecting and making decisions in the current AI revolution, the “Big Data” boom of the last decade, or Borges’ 1941, we’re still restricted by the same conditions. No amount of technological advancement can replace our core need for coherence, not completeness, in data. On the contrary, the limitless supply will make our disciplined approach all the more necessary.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="software"/><category term="science"/><category term="ontologies"/><category term="standards"/><category term="omics"/><category term="multiomics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Data is meaningless without context and our role as scientists is to provide that relationship.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific Babylon</title><link href="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/scientific-babylon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific Babylon"/><published>2026-01-10T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-10T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/scientific-babylon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://insilijo.github.io/blog/2026/scientific-babylon/"><![CDATA[<p>In accounts from The Bible and The Torah, the Tower of Babel is built to prevent a second flood, only to result in the fragmentation of human language. Variations on the same theme appear across Greek, Estonian, Sumerian, and Aztec traditions: a once-unified humanity loses a shared understanding of the world through linguistic division. In these stories, collective power gives way to confusion: not through catastrophe, but through meaning itself.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-right"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/tower_of_babylon-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/tower_of_babylon-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/tower_of_babylon-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/tower_of_babylon.jpg" width="100%" height="auto" alt="The Tower of Babel By Pieter Brueghel the Elder - Levels adjusted from File:Pieter_Bruegel_the_Elder_-_The_Tower_of_Babel_(Vienna)_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg, originally from Google Art Project., Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=22179117" title="The Tower of Babel By Pieter Brueghel the Elder - Levels adjusted from File:Pieter_Bruegel_the_Elder_-_The_Tower_of_Babel_(Vienna)_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg, originally from Google Art Project., Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=22179117" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">The Tower of Babel By Pieter Brueghel the Elder - Levels adjusted from File:Pieter_Bruegel_the_Elder_-_The_Tower_of_Babel_(Vienna)_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg, originally from Google Art Project., Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=22179117</figcaption> </figure> <p>Modern linguistics offers a less mythic explanation. Languages diverge naturally, shaped by ecology, geography, isolation, and social structure. Language is not merely a labeling system; it is a lens for interpreting a complex world. As perspectives diverge, so too must the structures used to describe them.</p> <p>Science faces a related, but sharper, problem. We attempt to describe systems that are not only complex, but mostly unobservable, probabilistic, and dynamic. The challenge extends past measurement and into representation: data are meaningless without a structured, shared, and preserved system. That system has to subscribe to the same orders as all data: Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reproducible (FAIR) because its value lies in how it interfaces with colleagues and other data.</p> <p>Ontologies attempt to resolve this fragmentation by enforcing shared meaning. Here, ontology is used in its applied sense: not as a claim about what exists, but as a practical expression of how knowledge is organized and exchanged. In practice, they often expose the cost of assuming meaning can be fixed at all. Applying an alternative standard to these processes – instead of resulting in meaning – adds another standard on top of the dozens already there. We confront our own Tower of Babel, then: we find ourselves playing a massive, expensive game of telephone where meaning is exchanged, lost, and mutated between experts.</p> <p>In metabolomics alone, biological, chemical, and analytical vocabularies coexist; each developed in different ecologies, each optimized for a different audience, and each only partially compatible with the others.</p> <p>These ontologies operate <strong>long before</strong> interpretation is even possible. Moreover, each individual discipline involved is nuanced, requiring years of experience or education to get to foundational understanding. These ontologies are the connective tissue that flattens these disciplinary nuances. For example, metabolomics data flows from Liquid Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (LC/MS) through reference spectra (ideally developed on the same machine and method) and finally to a format that’s accessible to a biochemist (typically a table). Even in this simplified process, it’s clear that there’s a substantial amount of effort involved in developing the method, creating the infrastructure around managing/storing the data, selecting/synthesizing reference compounds, analyzing data, and engineering it for interpretation.</p> <p>Even getting to the point where we’re comfortable analyzing the data requires a tremendous amount of effort and coordination. Moreover, no scientist has the capacity or time to ensure quality of the product, and relies on the data originator to deliver precise, accurate, and relevant results. It’s crucial, for both internal and external purposes, to maintain a paper trail that makes it clear how each step integrates into the useful data. Otherwise, we’re left with a mess of isolated numbers.</p> <figure class="inline-figure inline-left"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/xkcd_927_standards-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/xkcd_927_standards-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/xkcd_927_standards-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2026-01-01/xkcd_927_standards.png" width="360" height="auto" alt="xkcd 927 Standards comic" title="xkcd 927 Standards comic" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption small">xkcd 927 &quot;Standards&quot; by Randall Munroe, CC BY-NC 2.5, https://xkcd.com/927/</figcaption> </figure> <p>This isn’t just a factor in metabolomics. In fact, this specific analytical example can be applied directly to proteomics with a few small tweaks. Genomics, too, can claim to have done an excellent job of exploiting integrated analytics and ontologies to create reliable, consistent pipelines that are broadly interpretable and trustworthy. What we’re trying to do here – use extremely expensive, sensitive instruments on extremely expensive, sensitive biological samples – is difficult and important. The first step is being able to adequately describe what’s going on to other people.</p> <p>Ontologies are, at their most useful, a representation of shared purpose among diverse methods, all integrating into a cohesive representation of an intractable phenomenon. To get to that point, it requires often silent, detailed labor from a large group of people to map out and maintain a reliable pipeline. However, they can often fall prone to overly-calcified standards, resulting in a labyrinthine branched set of systems. These processes must reflect their application while remaining integrated with their partners. To do this, ontologies are most effective when they constrain interpretation without attempting to freeze meaning. In domains that evolve as quickly as medicine, chemistry, tech, and biology, representation must remain thoughtfully provisional without becoming unstable.</p> <p>What looks like a problem of standards is often a problem of governance. The failure mode here is rarely technical. It is organizational. Different groups optimize for different incentives, audiences, or realities – speed, precision, publication, novelty, regulatory defensibility, commercial relevance – and ontologies become the battleground where those incentives collide. Standardization does not remove ambiguity; it decides who bears the cost of resolving it.</p> <p>In practice, governance does not mean tighter standards or different hiring practices. It means deciding who can revise definitions, how translation is handled, and where ambiguity is tolerated. Meaning will change regardless; the real question is who is accountable for managing that change over time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="software"/><category term="science"/><category term="ontologies"/><category term="standards"/><category term="omics"/><category term="multiomics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An essay on how meaning, incentives, and governance shape scientific systems across teams and institutions.]]></summary></entry></feed>